Prudential Insurance Company as you know
is one of the top five largest group
disability insurance companies and we've
handled probably well over a thousand
long-term disability insurance claims
against them but today I want to try to
educate potential clients about what
should you expect if you've already
exhausted your administrative remedies
meaning you filed an appeal with
Prudential you know they also offer a
voluntary appeal which means two appeals
which you don't have to do and you know
the next option is to file a lawsuit so
I want to talk about what is that
process like what are timeframes what
are the pros and cons what are the
difficulties how often do they get
resolved so that someone who's going
through this has an expectation as to
what they can't expect so let's start
with the you know the first question
about filing a lawsuit and really how
much time do you have to file that
lawsuit after you've been denied
actually Gregg that's it's a difficult
question it's kind of a case-by-case
situation it's usually on the statute of
limitations on these lawsuits it's
usually about three years from the date
of proof of loss which is not really a
set dating it can vary but usually it's
three or some a day to proof of loss or
like to get them filed as quickly as
possible so there's no question that we
didn't miss any statute of limitations
right because that's going to be the
first line of defense they're going to
say you didn't fire a lawsuit timely
right you're done right all right once
you get your lawsuit filed what's the
average time that these cases take the
playout usually after the lawsuit is
filed the defendant has about 21 days to
answer the complaint and then once that
answer is filed with the court the court
enters a scheduling order the order sets
out a bunch of deadlines for discovery
which there's not much in an ERISA case
but discovery mediation deadlines and
then a trial date so usually it's about
a year out nine months to a year out for
the court to set a trial date okay and
in ERISA what does that mean a trial
date a trial date for an ERISA case
simply means that it is there's no jury
trial this is just a judge reviewing
your administrative record and
determining whether the insurance
company was arbitrary and capricious
the denial of your claim alright let's
talk a little bit about this arbitrary
and capricious discretionary clauses
what are those and are those an
advantage or disadvantage for a
disability claimant well if the
insurance company has discretion in the
policy and it's determined that they
have discretion then the judge will
determine the basis on the case on the
basis of whether they were arbitrary and
capricious which means that they did not
have any reasonable basis to deny the
claim okay and what is that I mean if
the judge first find that they add that
the person was disabled and then
determines that they acted unreasonably
what are the judges remedies available
if the judge determines that the
insurance company was unreasonable in
their decision then what the judge can
do is award back benefits the back
benefits that are owed and then the
claimant goes back on claim for as long
as they can continue to be disabled or
the judge can order the back benefits
paid and then remand it back to the
insurance company for another review to
determine whether the claimant is still
disabled all right so it sounds like you
have a scenario where you can win the
battle and lose the war absolutely or
say because if they do what's called a
remand then it's going back to the
company and your time and then they get
another chance to review it
what if they review it and still say no
we're not paying what are the remedies
then well what usually happens if they
get another bite at the Apple they do
the review and they say hey we still
think that they're not disabled then
they may offer another appeal which then
takes you of 180 days to appeal that
which is a six month four month process
then after the appeal they have another
90 days to review so you're almost at
another year out again with an appeals
process and then you're back to the
drawing board meaning you have to file
another lawsuit it's kind of a vicious
cycle does their comic point in time
once you file a lawsuit does that mean
only a judge can make a decision or is
there another way that the claim could
be resolved absolutely many times
actually a majority of the time that we
filed lawsuits they usually settle for
some sort of lump sum settlement where
the insurance company will agree to pay
a lump sum in order to relinquish the
policy and
what does that mean Oh a lump sum
settlement it means that they'll pay you
a lump sum of money which you know
usually can include back benefits in
some future benefits and once that lump
sum is paid it's a settlement and when
sets paid you no longer have the policy
with the insurance company and so you're
done with them and theoretically you
could go work another job the next day
if you were done with them
absolutely in terms of Prudential I
would say that Prudential is one of the
companies that we probably see the most
litigated cases against yep I would
agree with that and there's a ton of
case law against Prudential you talked
about something a minute ago about if
they had discretion and I know that
we've argued throughout the country that
their policies don't contain discretion
right and what's the advantage to a
claim and if you're able to prove that
their policy does not have a valid
discretionary clause there's actually a
very big advantage if you can show that
the insurance company doesn't have
discretion like like I said before when
they when they do have discretion it's
an arbitrary and capricious review which
is a very difficult standard of review
to over to to get over but once it's de
novo that means the judge reviews the
cases with a fresh set of eyes meaning
he's basically the insurance company
reviewing all of the evidence from the
beginning and determining whether the
insurance company was wrong for denying
the case then the claimant at that point
has an upper hand okay so well at least
a level more or less a little more level
thank you so I don't want claimants you
know we're considering filing a lawsuit
or involved in a lawsuit I think wow
there's no way I'm going to win if
there's a discretionary clause because
we've won them many times and there's
claimants around the country that have
won these cases unfortunately you're not
on a level playing field the insurance
company has the upper hand but you with
good lawyering and you know a lawyer who
knows what he what he or she's doing and
know that the case law knows the ERISA
regulations you can definitely present a
very strong case to the court to show
hey this insurance company acted
unreasonably but if you have an attorney
who doesn't do ERISA you know it's just
moonlighting on an ERISA case because
they think they want to try something
different there's no way they're going
to know all the ERISA reg you
and the hundreds of ERISA cases that
have come out that need to be relied
upon in order to help prove the case
press so if you have a Prudential claim
whether it's an application an appeal a
lawsuit potentially a lump sum
settlement no matter what stage you're
at feel free to call any of our lawyers
about your claim we can help you
anywhere in the country one of the
things we didn't mention is that because
these claims are governed by ERISA we
can file a lawsuit in any court around
the country and we've we have filed them
in as far away as Hawaii Florida
California New York so we're all over
the country filing these cases and what
makes it easy for us to do that is that
the courts are our paperless now it's an
electronic filing you almost never have
to go to court because the judges don't
want to see you and the claimant never
ever has to go to court there's no
required appearance for the claimant so
it's important for you to understand
that because there won't be any
inconvenience whatsoever for the
claimant with the filing of a lawsuit so
give us a call any of our lawyers can
help you and we look forward to the
opportunity to work with you